[Music]
hello everybody
um tom owen daniel
my name's andrew um we're all together
here uh
to talk about i think we're here to talk
about um
in a sense we both have platforms you
guys have your technosocial platform
uh and and you're you know a bit younger
than we are
so there's a generational uh difference
between us
at the same time we're we're um
traveling in the same kind of
intellectual spiritual space in many
ways
i think um and me and tom uh
began um a website newscast called
parallax and i've been working with him
and blogging on that site and and we've
had you know big hopes and dreams for
we're building this site into into
something that i think will reflect
um a kind of a you know
we could say a new a paradigm a new the
new paradigm let's have media the new
paradigm
of online you know information
uh ideas something that's removed from
from woke that's removed from censorship
which is you know open and
and interesting and we're all i think
we're all trying to do that
i think right uh if everybody would
agree with that so i thought of
i thought of uh you know framing this
discussion as being a discussion about
what is this this new paradigm
right what is this what is this
let's say kind of shifting uh
ambiguous space that we're in right now
um you know
and uh tom is often speaking about
post-post-modernism what's after
post-modernism
uh on our site we often talk about uh
the exodus
from the big media platforms um
it's a term that me and alexander bard
use a lot uh
how to create the next exodus um we also
have
other terms that we you know we throw
around in our circles one is
is called the renaissance so we've been
talking about the exodus
from the big social media platforms
we've also been talking about
the renaissance and in in terms of
rediscovering let's say more primordial
notions and ideas and thoughts and um
and also in the last conversation we
thought it might be interesting to talk
about
alchemy which i believe i think
daniel you have an interest in that and
at least i do and that might be
also a subject of conversation so does
anybody want to
riff on on my introduction on what am
what i was going here
yeah let me pick up on that so totally
it does feel like we're at the end
of a time period of an age right um
there's a lot of conversations talking
about post-post-modernism trans
modernism metamodernism what what do we
call that which we are living in today
um i think the way that i would connect
that to perhaps alchemy
and would be something like you know one
of the things that alchemy
does as far as i can tell is
it works with the prime matter that is
human perception and one of the things
that i contend is that time is a feature
of human perception not of
reality so when we're talking about what
comes after post-modernism
we're assuming linear time
but to me the question is more like
who is capable of actually
putting down the foundations for that
which comes after post-modernism because
one of the features of postmodernism as
i guess we all kind of understand is
that it's saturated
it's the end of everything nothing is
new everything is in decay
late civilizational decay right a little
bit like the dark ages or
late rome and i feel like the ability to
put down the foundations for something
new is kind of what we are all kind of
doing
to name it precociously is perhaps less
interesting than
talking about how it can come to be and
and that's i guess
our interest in in alchemy especially in
the age of
of digital technology
okay oh and you have anything to say
about that you wanna
i think yeah like i might zoom back to
um
one of the things you said when you just
started off about this um
what this new paradigm kind of looks
like
and i think the way i always conceive
about this it's like okay
it's the media first it's this new
information communication technology
that has
really changed things um
the essay to read to start thinking
about this way
is um is jordan hall's essays which are
pretty much like
classic by now in whatever bubble this
is that we're existing within on
uh on the collapse of the blue church
right the idea that
human societies have always had to solve
the question of how to generate
coherence an example he gives is like if
you've got people rowing a boat if
you've got
one person or two persons people rowing
a boat you can kind of just keep each
other in time but
when you've got 50 people in a boat how
do you get them all to row at the same
time
well you get someone else to beat the
drum or to
call the song or whatever it is that
then allows the other 50 to stay in time
with
now woody contends is the blue church
structure is the way that
that was done in the mass modern
societies was with
big broadcast monodirectional media
structures so
broadcasting they go out like it met
like from to all directions but then
also monodirectional there's
a speaker or a very few speakers who
then transmit their message to a large
population and essentially that was the
way that the 20th century was able to
the 20th century nations were able to
manage themselves whether the communist
ones or
the capitalist ones there was a media
infrastructure that allowed for a shared
sense of reality
in the uk we had the right-wing press
and the left-wing press and a few tv
channels
but there was basically a shared reality
tunnel that everyone existed within with
a few bit of contentions
um what happens with the internet with
youtube with podcasting is that shared
reality is utterly gone
i was talking to someone about it once
he was talking about how when he was a
just a guy in his 40s or 50s in the uk
we have a tv show called
top of the pop so we used to have and it
was like the pop musicians of the day
would come on and do a video and he said
everyone would watch that because it was
the cool thing that was on
now what's happened today there is no
top of the pops there is no one thing
that everybody watch in fact there's
[ __ ] millions of things that
everybody watches and in some way that's
great because it's like
ultimate personalized consumer media
entertainment
but in the other sense there is no
longer
a shared cultural mythos that everybody
belongs to
and what i would suggest is that in
these supposedly secular 19th 20th
century societies when they're
supposedly atheists but really
the media culture served as the new
mythos the new religion and
that church hence jordan hall is terming
at a blue church right
that church has fragmented and where we
are now is that
we're beginning to experiment with the
new
multi-directional media where everybody
has a voice i mean the most obvious
examples of this on twitter and facebook
but the problem is i mean alexander is
great at laying this out everybody's
screaming
that's alexander by the way the
philosopher yeah he calls those sites
that
child diseases or something or
children's diseases or
you know because there's narcissism kind
of run amok
or right everybody's screaming and
competing for likes and attention but
there's actually
not much meaningful content being
produced
or if it is it just gets drowned in the
sludge
but with things like zoom and with
podcasting and with youtube and with
mailing lists and other formats that we
don't even know of yet there's the
possibility for doing something more
which is i think
trying to establish real meaningful
intellectual spaces to begin to ponder
like
okay [ __ ] what the [ __ ] is going on and
where do we go now
okay tom what about why don't you talk
about parallax or
you know the vision the intellectual
vision of parallax in relation to to
what
these guys have been have been saying
perhaps is that possible well
well i had some some technical
difficulties so i didn't get the first
part of
of uh what you guys were saying but the
general idea
you know what i see i i i just saw
yesterday this phenomenal podcast
between
joe rogan and and douglas murray you
know and
and you know the problems of of the left
and
and the the reaction it provokes in a
kind of way
and then you have you know this complete
disconnect between
media and the reality and what's
happening within the
united states and between europe and and
and the united states
and you know to answer your question you
know to to have some
sane perspectives uh on what's going on
in the world and some sense making that
that is something that drives me and i
won't i would like to do this with with
parallax
you know just because it's just you know
to try to create a more meaningful
picture of what's going on
in the world you know not in this left
wing mainstream
uh focus on on
just a tiny part of the world you know
and so
um i i don't know it's it's it's just a
mess out there you know and and
um so so some some sane
and and rational and
and yeah
in this respect progressive views on
where we can go
individually and and socially so
i don't know it's interesting you're
using that term
in a positive light because a term is
such a has such negative connotations
you know these days it's sort of being
progressive has
has become a kind of um if you're
progressive you're kind of reactionary
or something these days it's kind of
weird there's this
inversion of everything yeah um right if
you're if you're super left-wing you're
you're you're
you're reactionary conservative and if
you're conservative now you're
you're somehow radical uh you know on
some level you're like the cutting edge
like
douglas murray or something he's he's a
conservative right
right he's the cutting edge what um so
so
it's it's it's it's a weird sort of uh
inversion
right i like the that that you guys
mentioned
um progress and i want to bring it back
to what that the word church
used by owen and jordan hall previously
because to me this is really a
theological question so in the same way
that perhaps at the
start of the 20th century god died as
bernice
um there was a theological transition of
ways of being in the world
and one of the things that i contend is
that
it is the prerogative and the mission
of theological constructs to generate
reality
to generate ways of seeing the world the
previous one the blue church
said that progress and the belief in the
future
is the way to go that that future is
really about maximizing pleasure
reducing pain and it
put down certain guidelines that were
sort of the dogmas of the age right
um dugan criticizes this obviously from
his point of view but the critique
is nonetheless notable when he he says
that the dogmas of the time of the 20th
century of the blue church includes
something like
human rights like the dogmatic category
of the individual which is so
ontologically generative
uh that we cannot even conceive of it
because we are to it like fish are too
water
we don't you know in other times and
other places people might consider the
world to be based around
family or or the the parish or the clan
but today you know our responsibilities
rather than
than rights to you know exactly
or your how you contribute to the
society right
not as an individual but how you
contribute to this to uh
you know um how you are of service to
the society
rather than just trying to get your
rocks off or something like that
exactly and and this is not even i would
sort of expand on that and say that it's
not even only
framing the relationship of the
individual to the society
it's framing the way that the individual
creates itself as a subject in other
words
to say individual as a word is already a
way to subject to subjectify
to frame that being in a relationship of
power
to frame that being in a view of time
that's also the heideggerian way of
really going to the depth of really how
are we even talking about these things
let's question them
more deeply uh and there's a lot of
unasked questions behind the
you know the emergence of something like
the blue church and
it's its consequences leading up to
today and sort of the cultural
warfare situation that we include
ourselves in
and so that's why owen and i always come
back again to
this idea of alchemy this idea of
ontological designing
as a potential solution because it's the
recognition that
the theological dogmas that frame how we
even consider
ourselves subjects are something that
is in crisis and we need to step up and
obviously that's what we're trying to do
with with platforms and conversations
like this
to really try to not only figure out
what might be a way that we could share
but even the
the way we talk about that is generative
ontologically
i want to know a little bit about what
you mean by alchemy um
because alchemy is is normally
considered sort of a prototype of
science and
full of all kinds of superstition and
that but i
i think the appeal of alchemy is that it
doesn't
you can play more it's not so reductive
as as
you know mechanical science uh uh can be
in other words
it it it it doesn't it's the imagination
the imaginative aspect is your the
subjective imaginative aspect is
included
you know in the experiment right
uh uh with with the objects um
so so so the way that that
we use the term alchemy is in a way kind
of
uh interchangeable with ontological
design which is the idea that
we are performing changes in perception
and and the subjectivity of the being
itself and by framing perhaps the
individual within a set of relationships
with
objects ideas worldviews
technologies by curating this
relationship we're actually designing
the individual we're not designing
magazines we're not designing
chairs we're not designing architecture
we're designing people
and that's really [ __ ] big mind shift
well because the medium is the message
i'm sorry to interrupt again in other
words the the the platforms that we're
creating here like parallax and
and and all that and uh and techno
social that that is
that is an alchemical human you know
creation of some
sort which you interface with and and
and and changes you on some levels
precisely
because the mimetic apparatuses that we
instantiate and create through these
platforms
are the very means by which people
process
energy by which they sort of equilibrate
or balance their sex economy if you want
to quote wilhelm wright
it's the way that they are that they are
subjects
all right that this just goes down boils
down to the simple uh heideggerian idea
that
subject and objects are the same that
there's not
actually any difference which is not
only hagarin but also post-human
anyway which is um you know my clothes
and myself what's the difference right
they're an extension of my skin
the glasses are an extension of our
eyesight and so there's a deep
intimate relationship between ourselves
and technology and you know 2020 we
might as well look into that
because that has generative properties
for reality
which is of course fascinating because
it brings us into a way of
seeing that is quite ancient in the
world and has been
kind of dismissed by much of the
progressive rational paradigm which is
you know there's many names for it like
animism would be one of them like
just spirituality would be another i
think in contemporary philosophy there's
a movement called agential realism which
is
like moved by people like karen barrett
and a couple of others essentially the
idea being that
there is something animate in all
matter and indeed in all
or supposedly objective properties some
some unfolding
thing which again is like the
heideggerian language right
and i find this
super intriguing to to begin to actually
like
to ask what it was that enabled people
to to experience the world in such a way
and how then they
they tamed that experience of perception
and you know we are back there whether
or not we we admitted are not just
having a phone
in your pocket means that the world is
speaking at you constantly and unless
you've got the like
absolute [ __ ] resistance to your
notifications i've got them turned off
and you just get drawn to interpret and
i i've been spending myself listening to
podcasts a lot of the time at the moment
so i walk around and in some sense
plastic is speaking to me at every
moment i'm hearing human voices in every
direction and
i mean that was the case when we had
radio and television but i don't think
it's
ever been quite so pronounced at least
in recent times
that the world is literally speaking to
us and throwing communication to us in
all directions
in all different formats at all
different times
there's this animistic way of being and
alchemy
begins to then be in the context that
we're thinking about it like
the discipline of starting to to go okay
the world is alive again what the [ __ ]
do we do about it
precisely let me read you something very
quickly that i took from
from nick lands from one of his websites
uh how does the press warn the public
about
demons arising from a master algorithm
without making it sound like a magical
spell
with great difficulty because the actual
bedrock of reality may not only be
stranger than the narrative supposes
but stranger than it can suppose so this
speaks to our
uh tools to relate to reality whereas
the reality tunnels of you know the blue
church tell us that you know that we are
individuals and we have
our own wills and rights and there's
superstition and there's science and
there's reality well today
as owen said the stones are coming alive
that's all mixed
that's all mishmash superstitions the
ghosts the phantasm the fantasies
they're all mixing together and coming
alive in a way we're being haunted
through these
black mirrors uh not only the black
mares that maybe
uh john d used to describe the
nokian language when he was working for
queen elizabeth
as agent 07 but also the black mirrors
that we carry in our pockets
spreading this schizophrenic mind aids
as i saw
again on a meme
yeah the black mirrors yeah right
remember it remembers me of of raul
escherman's performatism
which is an approach after post
postmodernity have you ever read about
that
yes because this performative act to
create
beauty and truth although we know that
it can't be true but to live with this
duality in a way and do it anyhow and to
explain
something of value and to to change our
perceptions
and to change the world by that and so
that
sounds uh like a pretty alchemic
approach to that precisely that's that's
the idea of artistically mediated belief
right uh and i think that it gets a
little bit hard
the only thing i mean i i don't know
performativism that well but my only the
slight gripe i have
although i agree with the basic idea
behind it is that the word
the idea of performance itself is
already
slightly ironic it's like when you
perform you are doing
something other you are pretending in a
sense
and i think that it's almost
anti-hydarian or something right
heidegger was always talking about the
what is it that the word the german word
the authenticity
and that this constant disclosure
towards authenticity
rather and if you just define life as a
big performance and everything being
fake
um well well andrew but i'm sorry to
interrupt you but the great
god of of movie stars uh marlon brando
he says like all life is acting and
in the sense well that's true as well
yeah i think
that's again where it comes when it
comes full circle where you know i just
watched the movie tennis so forgive me
for doing this gesture but where past
and
and future just come together and bind
in this really weird way because the
question is
is there anything other than performance
foucaults at the same time all the
postmodern say the same thing right
is there anything outside of power is
there anything that is not a power
relationship
you know to name something to say that
something should be true and something
should not be true
isn't that yet another recursive
repetition of the same old story that
is the story that we perform roles for
each other
that we theorize stories within which we
live that we create these spiritual mind
temples that we're supposed to inhabit
and the thing that i would bring up is
that the
theological ability capacity talents
resources to be able to create these say
performances worth living is um
is pretty [ __ ] big and scary and hard
it's very pathetic it lies behind the
bard absolute it is not for those who
want
it is not for the many it is for the few
and i'm not really even sure
that um i'd like to sort of pierce that
fail and then put my head through that
right even nietzsche said something like
for the lovers of the light
stay in the shadow something like that
so point being
it's not a it's very serious to create
these
time mind temples within which we might
live which is perhaps the task that
we're
collectively trying to address uh as
we're looking
past the time horizon of the fall of
whatever postmodernism represents
um yeah that was well said i i think
this kind of
seriousness you're talking about often
gets forgotten you know
when we speak about all these things
because they're so salient and
you know attractive and you know there's
this bright light pulling us towards
something and
um it's incredibly hard we have to
become
kind of uh i don't know we have to be
able to stand like
i'm speaking a bit metaphorically here i
feel forgiving but
we have to kind of stand in the middle
of the chaos and not be you know torn to
pieces
if that makes any sense that's precisely
yeah i mean like
the idea that's come up the images
coming into my head about this
performatism
is like the distinction say between
let's say like
guns and roses going up and performing
as guns and roses and slash an axle
slash an axle versus
some cover band going up and performing
as like guns two roses and putting on a
wig to look like the front man and to
look like the lead guitarist
you know the second one are doing
performance of performance there's like
a second order mimeticism there
whereas like the uh in the former case
like guns and roses
are actually doing the real thing they
are just expressing themselves
artistically
so they are performing but they're doing
it in a way that's like
that is that is the expression where the
the second order performance is like
performing as them does that make some
sense oh yeah
well well i think the interesting thing
about what you're saying i mean if you
if you're
rolling stones and you're singing for 40
years satisfaction
i i wouldn't describe there a little
no more meaning than if some cover band
would do it because it's devoid of any
meaning at that point
yeah that's right so but there what what
i wanted to say there
like different definitions of
performatism and i don't know but we're
it's unattended here but there's this
performance you speak of you perform as
a band
made like a cover band then you have
like the post-modern notion of it
where you can like in in a butlerian way
where you
uh perform agenda by by now
announcing it by a woman giving birth
like
as a speech act and then you have this
postmodern notion of performatism why
where you are engaging say with a
with an artifact with a piece of art and
you're creating some new
world view or some new experience or
some new
form of looking looking at the world and
with the world in this height
heideggerian sense and so these are
different notions of
what performance yeah and so it's you
know
well but back to guns and roses um i
think that
i think that um the the trick is or the
difficulty is
is that in the beginning you have you
you have this inspiration that comes
kind of from
a primordial place and you take a risk
and you put yourself out there
and then you become a caricature of
yourself afterwards right
uh you become a you you just and you get
further and further from that state
of uh you know inspiration which never
you know the ends off in the jewish
tradition means without
end right or the you know uh this this
this state of creativity without end and
i think the alchemical
task is is tapping into that state
yeah it's very hard when you're working
with structures right because
because because you get attached to a
structure and that structure becomes
reified
and you know you get some some you get
some feedback by and then the structure
starts to take to take you over so
maybe um the art of making a structure
that
that that works um is finding a way
to to keep that ever that that ends off
that
spirit without end you know let me riff
on that so
performance uh irving goffman this
canadian guy
uh used to talk about performances as
being this ubiquitous element of
everyday life when you go to a pharmacy
to buy some
medicine uh it's it's normal that the
people there sometimes are wearing like
white robes but why they don't need to
they're not in the lab it's a
performative aspect so do priests
sometimes it's it really has this charge
of being a prop in a ritual
or the front or a setting in this
performance
right uh the performances of everyday
life great book and they
they actually um have a function which
is a function to mediate
the flows and perhaps the let's call it
this
extended shared libidinal economy the
meaning economy of everyone right
there's a reason why they wear a coat
because there's a charge of credibility
to it because there's a charge of
hygiene cleanliness etc but you pointed
to something really cool
which was like um talking about
not so much the functional profane
rituals and the performances
like you know going to a pharmacy and
getting some medicine and the guy being
wearing a white robe
but the the other perhaps more spiritual
uh or more meaning dense
performances so the other day i went to
a church here in gdansk in
in poland and i was amazed that how
you know throughout europe time and
again you find these amazing cathedrals
these these huge buildings
with with such holiness with such charge
uh and i was talking to my friend and i
was
you know i'm i'm i was
sort of reinforcing that spiritual
charge of the place that that beauty of
the place then he made a very good point
which is
yeah but um do you think everyone who
went to church and goes to church
actually understands
the depth of the spirituality as you are
trying to explain right now or
did they just follow the ritual because
everyone else did it and just followed
the exoteric
part of the doctrine without really
understanding the esoteric part of the
doctrine
and that's a great point so you alluded
to that andrew which is
i would say the following uh it is for
the few to understand the esoteric
to be the channelers of the paints off
the dimensions and to craft that into
exoteric symbols
that then you know if they're well
crafted enough then perhaps you're
actually building a holy word building a
temple building a symbolic house where
everyone else can live now
if there's no holiness at the core then
god has left the temple
he will not return and all that's left
is rot and ruins and the desert
coming over and covering up the sphinx
yeah whilst popping yeah
your mention of the church brings up
something which is a big
difficulty in the design of society's
big and small and indeed
cultures and subculture
cults which is that the strength of the
organization
is something like equivalent to the
amount of authenticity that each of the
top participants brings to it
and the larger it gets the more it
scales the more people
will end up showing up for just this
like social decorum for example
going to church because that's what you
do when you go to church
or going to work because you get paid to
go to work and responsibly you know you
go to a job interview and they say
why do you want to work in this job and
you come up with some [ __ ] reason
about how you've always wanted to be a
chef
or a a teacher but the truth is it's
like
well in most cases it's because i i need
to earn money
and now i need to say something good to
make you think that i'm at least good
enough at lying so that other people
will believe that i want to be in this
space
whereas building a a
the advantage of building a small sector
a secret society
and i believe this is the reason the
secret societies have existed throughout
the
to create a little closed container
where the
libido energy and attraction is such
that everybody
is devoting a lot of themselves to what
might be achieved in that space
yeah and well it's true that the um the
esoteric
uh is always uh you know governed by a
certain kind of elitism
right it's iliteraterian if that's a
word
it's not egalitarian and it never can be
and
that's just the way it is because
there's only a certain amount of people
that want to step that close to the fire
right so so so so
in in a traditional society people would
understand that
you know they would they would
understand uh that you know you're
you're cut out for that or you're not
and so if you're not cut out for that
you do other things and you you have an
ordinary life
and you know within the realm but there
there is a central core there is as as
you express so well daniel there is this
kind of burning
uh there's this hearth and there's fire
that that you
that you you you are receiving the the
blessings from from from
from that just just just by being a good
person or doing whatever you do
um but the problem today is that
everybody wants to kind of get into the
esoteric
uh and nobody wants to to do the the
preliminaries the steps that that are
required
to become there so everybody thinks you
have access to
to uh i don't know maybe maybe that
maybe i'm being you know conservative
when i'm talking like that or something
but
i agree with you i think you're very
pragmatic let me
throw something to that which i wholly
agree with what you said right there is
there's
here's a thought there's perhaps two
ways to address or to reach
um this inner burning core or rather to
reach the core
of the alchemical pursuit one of them is
through heart
because of the law of equivalent
exchange right there's no free lunch you
have to get something in return and you
can give a lot of time a lot of effort
time is the only wealth that doesn't
scale right so you can give some of your
time some of your efforts study
discipline
self-control etc sacrificing uh
sacrifices
and their self-sacrifice but there's
also sacrificing the libido which is
stored
in other institutions that's why
breaking rules
er is kinky and gives people like a a
sort of a sexual charge
i think that's or that's why
you know so many cultures throughout the
ages have sacrificed living beings
for the sake of their gods because
that's
when you kill the lamb ritualistically
speaking perhaps inside the holy of
holies in in this core
close ritual behind the bar absolute
you're
you're doing that same effort which you
know i don't know if
there needs to be sort of a sacrifice
that's my whole point and that sacrifice
can be one of two types that
you can you can it's either
self-sacrifice or
or heterosacrifice in the vajrayana
tradition you
you it's it you you you um
you give samadhi intense concentration
right
of an object or something like that and
and that is how
that's how you transform trends that's
how you offer your your
labenus or your um your energy
to you know uh to to
the fire so to speak right um but
you know in the more archaic religions
uh you would do this cheap thing where
you would you would
use you would make the offering of
somebody else of the scapegoat
in order to pay that debt right yeah and
to tie back to
to tom and parallax uh you know we're
living in a time of chaos we're living
in a time where
uh the instincts to sacrifice something
else that is out there for the sake of
some personal gain
is rampant and it gets chaotic because
you want to burn the collective
accumulated capital of
the sacrifices of you know a lot of
people and a lot of things
and there's something to be gained out
of that perhaps more instantly but
it's it's it's the fire that burns very
brightly but perhaps does not sustain
itself
does that make sense yeah uh
well the fact that it doesn't sustain
itself i think it does sustain itself
but but it doesn't need it doesn't i
mean it's always
already present in everything
but but it it's it's it's a human life
that burns itself out
somehow um or at least it burns itself
until there's no longer
anything to burn uh elephant levi
this occultist mentioned in one of his
books like the history of magic i think
that's
you know uh at the time when the the
jews were prisoners in babylon
there were these babylonian kings who
are
i think the magi and i'm just trying to
relate the story and i'm
probably butchering them but the idea
was that they knew or someone there was
warned that
cyrus quote unquote the great was
outside of the walls and it was going to
go in and wasn't gonna let
pillage and ransack and conquer the city
but they chose to do nothing
i think was the prophet daniel who
warned them and they chose to do nothing
but
to throw they instead chose to throw
this last orgy
to go out in a dying bang and an orgy
that immediately
lights so bright that even the skies
looked like
they were day and it was actually the
night something like that and then they
died
and with them all their secrets and this
kind of happened again in the fall of
rome again right
you can you can there's
early stage civilizations mid-stage
civilizations there's late-stage
civilizations uh
everything has kind of this life cycle
the word life being essential here
and i think that's what we're navigating
through
honestly at this point in history
yeah do you hear me do you hear me with
with my phone now
yeah yeah all right that was actually
something that dr murray said in the
in the podcast yesterday let me come
back to that because he said
uh historically speaking it's a sign of
end of a civilization
if topics like identity politics and uh
trans issues take uh uh first ring
amongst other things you know and so
that's like you can see that
when the uh greek empire
fall fell and and their
emphasis on on you know gender topics at
that time and so that's quite
interesting
and yeah i thought well just just you
know everything splinters into into
little you know groups and factions and
tribes and exactly yes and then
everybody's at each other's throat
it's the war of all against war i i mean
war of all against all
but i wonder i wonder why that what what
gender has to
do with that that that's that's my
question
i think it has to do with the uh uh
technology has a role to play in this
i'm going to connect mark fisher and
occultism so
he did it already whatever but like
hauntology this idea that we are
haunted by the fantasies or in french
fantasma
of um surplus libido that finds no
vessel
to be held with it and when that vessel
is broken
vessels that are uh for example power
apparatuses in society institutions like
marriage
or things like old gender roles they
were vessels vessels have the property
to constrain and oppress but they also
hold something together when you break
that vessel
it's like the pandora's box is open the
exactly
yeah the pattern it goes wide open at
the moment right yeah
if you can deconstruct the most basic
perceptions we have
like uh we are for men and not for
like uh other identities and
and disrupt that kind of perspective
then you can
deconstruct basically everything
precisely
and that is a demonic force in that
sense because it's it's just
it's it's a process of continual
fragmentation
and uh and and you know uh
and and ripping apart people's most
common sense axiomatic
views of themselves you know ordinary
people in the world being
you know assaulted by subhuman messaging
on some level you know that makes them
doubt everything about themselves and
you know from their health to their sex
to you know whatever right
precisely yeah well look the
contemporary capitalist society mark
fisher makes this point in capitalist
reasonism i think it's just
very essentially unsatisfying
like never before has bad subjectivity
in the lacanian sense been more deeply
felt by people and so
they're clinging for something that
feels
real that feels legit that feels
authentic and
like gender is one of the oldest things
we have
capitalism it predates feudalism it
predates tribalism basically
and and it's also worth pointing out
that actually us guys here we're also
quite interested like andrew and i both
involved with the men's movement tom
i don't know quite how connected with
you you are as well but fragger like
daniel i've mentioned it to you a couple
of times it's like
there is also a positive project along
these alignment of gender lines it's
like we're not standing here
observing that that the current point is
devol or devolving and just
collapsing the people bickering about
genders but there is also something very
real about that gender polarity that
needs to be
investigated and primed into you know we
also see
um andrew you just spoke to rachel
haywire and
raven connolly right like they're doing
this project like
the philosopher queens which i find
super interesting in
main part just because there's a lot of
male voices in this space doing
philosophy work and
i'm intrigued to see what sort of
femininity they might be able to uncover
that goes beyond the the identitarian
feminism
not feminism but female perspective
mm-hmm yeah
yeah yeah yeah there's a few things to
say about that is
is um in the state of total
fragmentation
you know people just you know there's
the war of all against all and
and and and there's the you know the
society falling apart
but then there's you know first
mountains and rivers are mountains
rivers then they're not and then they
have to become mountains and rivers
again with a capital m and a capital r
right they have to so we have that there
has to be a new synthesis right i guess
it's a hegelian thing as well right
within that negativity there has to be a
new synthesis so there has to be um
a new concretion or or you know using
this hegelian language of something
which
which would be it would it would be it
would be both a return
and it would also it would also be a
path forward
and me and alexander have been speaking
of this as being the exodus myth
in a sense that's what the culture is
missing in exodus myth like a way out of
this you could say identitarian
uh you know uh you know stomach eating
itself or
brain eating itself or zombie kind of
apocalypse or whatever you want to call
it it's just like
a a landscape of total nihilism
uh and then and then um and then
so there is this need to rediscover uh
the exodus myth
yeah and you don't have that and what i
mean by the exodus myth is
not necessarily a there's a social level
to that there's
there's there's an inner outer and a
secret level to that you know there's
there's there's there's the getting out
of the the paradigm
present paradigm and then there's also
you know liberating
yourself in some kind of way so you
actually have a constructive view and
have a
forward vision and how to have a have a
you know
have to have discovered a
constructive meaning and mission in your
life which is
you know we talk about as being the
phallic um
which is very counter-intuitive to the
the discourse that's out there which is
is
is all about sort of um
sort of you know healing our you know
healing our wounds
yeah i think right if i if i if i may
because that's something
that i was thinking about all day you
know i was partaking
at some forum metamodern forum and so
there was a question you know what is
metamodernism
and you know it was all you know about
oscillating i
i will fit this in in our uh current
conversations like what is
meta-modernism it's an oscillation
between you know modernism and
post-modernism
and and you know the the the thing the
the paradigm is pretty similar to what
wilbur
was doing the integrating what what came
before
but you know my my my impulse but my
thinking
is is that you know additionally to the
integration would come came before
because all these
previous movements like feminist
movements they all have their purpose
but you know if you talk about emergence
there's still something there's
something new that is not
necessarily um the re it is the result
of the past but it's still something new
you know you can't uh explain it solely
by
uh looking at the past there's a new
information which which makes the thing
um interesting and intriguing it's like
a new piece of art
and you don't understand it but it's a
new paradigm and you can't really
explain
metamodernism or integral just by
looking at the past and integrating the
previous stages of
of of development but there has to be a
new
a new quality you know and so and so and
i i feel that
that is what we're talking about like
what what could it be
you know like is it phallic is it like
is it like a
palpable uh a new vision for the future
you know some performative act and so
and
and and i feel like in those circles
this new
aspect of emergence is kind of missing
because they're just looking at the past
year
you have to integrate modernism the good
parts and then the good parts of
post-modernism
but that's not sufficient you know it's
there there's
there's missing something it doesn't
take into account the
the the novelty and also also the venus
energy
um yeah and the masculine it's the
masculine
[Music]
i'm glad that we wound up here because
it's something i think about a lot which
is just like i have this kind of like
intuitive dislike of the
modern framing and that's like i
appreciate the point and what it's
trying to do and establish itself as a
new era but
for one thing it feels like it's just
played more games with prefixes we're
just going to throw better on it to show
that we've gotten bigger and for
all of the thinkers who are considered
post modern didn't really name their
project post-modernism that was
something that came
after but then there's also this sense
that
the idea of modernism i believe is about
conquering territory so the modern
project kind of quite explicitly you
know as expansionist
and they were gonna use rationality and
science to do these things
then post-modernism was almost about
conquering modernism itself by turning
this very intellectual critique on its
language games
and pulling it apart and now the meta
modern seem to think that
if we can just recognize that then we
can conquer it all
and then we're going to be all right and
i think that's
precisely the wrong point to look at you
know daniel you said something to me
that i felt very deeply the other day
which is like
in some deep sense we have to accept
that we've lost
we've lost to techno capital it's a
beast that is [ __ ]
run and growing up from winning us and
it's kind of taken us over
and so i was writing about this in the
email fred earlier it's like
there's this weird hegelian inversion
where just at the point where
modern man thought he was going to take
over the world with his machines they've
turned around and consumed him
and now we're all in the belly of this
new digital goddess [ __ ] beast
and we're like what the [ __ ] yeah yeah
interesting because we were we had a
discussion today on uh about i
i i was reading this guy's book
catalastim
and his formula was you know modernism
post-modernism and then
trans modernism and i jumped on that
because i thought i thought
at least it has the transcendental
aspect in it where we're modern
where metamodernism seems like a lot of
jacking off to me like
if i can be a little bit blunt like uh
um
whereas the transcendental right that's
you know like like uh
tom wrote a book about about will and
transcendence and
that that has some meat to it uh um
to me and then and then you were kind of
you objected a little bit because it
seemed like okay here's another prefix
or whatever and it's just another
game and you know that we can play and i
i could see your point as well but um
that i see this is that uh there's
there's two modes uh to look at it one
of them is
is that which show one intuitively
dislikes and which i
understand why he says that which is the
being against
term coining prematurely uh
and the other one which is which is i
think the juice of the matter which
we're all actually trying to get at
which is the hardest thing so
we try to look to the past and figure
out our frame is
the actual phallic energy of the
establishment of the edifying of the
constructing of the proper way to relate
to the chaotic landscape within which we
are engaged you know the acceleration is
talk about exit
um i have personally like you know
come hmm i lost your voice
is that just me or um
yeah i don't know if you i kept it but
maybe just rehash the point daniel
okay so the point is that
i i i i want to get to the point that is
uh domesticated
right pandora's box is open uh we live
in a chaotic
world all these memes all these ghosts
are haunting us from every side
so we were to uh creating these
these makeshift diy
names that we put onto reality to sort
of help us navigate it but i think that
at this point in history
at the very moment when we finish
perhaps naming the thing that we see
and put it out there that is already
outdated it's already over because of
speech because of acceleration
yeah the game is over the moment that
you put a name on so obviously
there's the other way which is the uh i
would call it more of a phallic delisian
way of engaging with the flux of how
things become and that's why i come back
to the applied science of domesticating
uh ghosts of the behaviorism
of um you know belief so so nick land
and and
guideboar and so many people speak about
intelligence having become autonomous as
a process so
our ghosts i keep coming back to the
idea that in french
fantasy or sexual fantasy is called
fantasma i don't know
if i'm right on this but i think they
they overlapping away and that just
that's precise why because this surplus
libido right that does not fit into the
old vessels has run amok
capitalism wants to make a buck out of
that so really incentivizes that
and so it just runs amok to the point
where all these ghosts this army of the
dead
is currently in charge of things we've
lost that battle and
i think that within the cacophony of
chaos the the right thing
or a worthwhile message that is more
towards the trend that you were saying
is necessary andrew
uh something edifying something
constructive something more phallic
something that is more about like okay
how do we
do things for me is to say that the
proper way to engage
is just talk about how to domesticate
how to
how to what do you mean by that as you
said domesticate
ghosts and and my mind went blank and i
i wasn't quite sure what you meant by
that
yeah so what i mean by that is that you
know our thoughts appear in our minds uh
uh not out of a void right there there's
a context
there's a memetic context there's a
discursive context
uh you know i have a name i use
sentences to have a predicate and a
subject that that's already like a thing
in itself the power as foucault said is
something that's embedded in everything
right
and what capitalism post-modernism did
is to basically throw that into
into chaos and technocapitalism is king
in doing that and obviously
let me see if i get this in a way that's
not too too confusing
and contrived the spectacle becomes
autonomous
all of the ideas that we have are
integrated into this the belly of the
large machine
and they transcend us they become too
large and in a sense
we are no longer and i we are
subservient to this machine we
all right the ideas that we have are not
our own the tastes
that we have are formed governed by men
that we have
largely never heard of this was said by
walter lipman in the in the 20s and the
30s this was said by bernays who by the
way is the nephew of freud
so already there he was intuiting this
this idea that
psychoanalysis was already getting to at
the time as well which is
yeah these ghosts these these will these
liberal
freaks are coming out of pandora's box
they're coming out of the old vessels
the old vessels are no longer good
enough right
the isms of the past become outdated
extremely fast and the rate at which
they become obsolete
is accelerating so that's why the art of
building the new vessels for me
is an art of domesticating desire of
designing
desire itself because right now
you know person a is doing philosophy
because they're
psychically and sexually impotent person
b is doing philosophy because they want
to get tricks in bad person c is making
philosophy because
you know maybe because they love truth
whatever motives and desires are so ex
so large right it's every marketing
department knows this they tap into this
they make a bucket of this and
i think that the creative thing to do to
edify is really to
construct and this construction will not
be
universal because there's no universal
mommy or daddy this will not be
distributed equally this will not be
it's gonna it's like settling a new
landscape really settling the new sphere
that's currently at war the war of
everyone against everyone that's what
dugan calls new machia
and i think that from that landscape
there's going to be
you know things happening after this
what i like about what you're saying and
and you mentioned and
uh you mentioned john d and you talk
about fantasma and
uh magic and and in our preliminary talk
we even talked a little bit about
crowley i have a friend who is like a a
professor in a university in berlin and
he had a order
of occult art right and so that was a
that was an order
for literature basically but they used
these old techniques to bring out new
forms of description of
of of fantasma you know
it was not just it was not just poetry
there was like a
a vivid a living thing being invoked
there and this is like one of these
great prerogatives of magic uh
still i think that that it can do that
you know that's
that it still uh offers the the tools
and the techniques to
you know crack open the the models of
the world that we have
and you know be confronted by the chaos
and to create something new in there
you know yeah i've been studying this
this
this form of uh you know hermetic cabela
recently and right the methodology is
interesting
um because okay you have these cards uh
and you you you you you you stare at an
image
you know in it you know it's it's
usually an alchemical image you know of
mercury and
sulfur and symbolized by the sun and the
moon and
you know actually the sun is feminine
and the moon is masculine and that and
that uh
and that which is i thought kind of
interesting and anyway
you look at this card which is a sort of
primordial design and you stare at it
and you allow your mind
to to um to uh and
you can use your intellect and an
associative mind to
to to to go deeper into this image and
you study it for several days like nine
days
um the first part of the meditation is
you study the these in
this image the second part of the
meditation is you visualize the image
and you try to keep it the image just
the pure visualization of the image
in silence and and you deepen the just
the perceptual
part of the image so it becomes more
embodied right that's the second stage
of the practice and the third stage of
the practice is you dissolve
everything uh and and usually there's
sort of a bliss that arises
and and and there's a kind of pure
creative spirit right that
that comes which can be anything it's
sort of in this dissolving stage
um and so i thought that that model uh
was was very very interesting in terms
of um
you know you know how we can we can we
can look at alchemy
and magic because there was nothing
particularly like uh
uh i don't know freak freaky but it was
all very
all very uh straight straight forward on
one level at the same time right
all right so we've we've been made
familiar to
this sort of way to relate to memes and
symbols because now
uh they saturate and permeate every
aspect of our lives
in other words the reason why pentagrams
and and little
horus eyes don't really work anymore
today in their magical
accursed character at least in the way
that we fantasize that use
that they used to in the past is because
they've become deflated
there's so many other symbols around
them that by sheer virtue of scale
like uh they they just don't have the
same impact in our
already calloused perception let me just
read something to you about
the mad prophet uh nick land who's for
me
nothing but an occultist talking about
technology
said what is concealed the occult
is an alien order of time which betrays
itself through coincidences
synchronicities and similar indications
of an intelligent
arrangements of fate i think this
connects to the cabal
deeply an example is the kabbalistic
pattern occulted in ordinary languages a
pattern that
cannot emerge without eroding itself
since the generalized human
understanding and the liberated usage
of letter clusters as numerical units
would shut down the channel of
coincidence i know this sounds a little
bit
weird but coincidence
also known as alien information so it's
only because people use
words without numerizing them that they
remain open as conduits for something
else
to dissolve the screen that hides such
things and by hiding them enables them
to continue
is diffused with the source of the
signal and liquidate the world
now for me this is this is a little bit
referring to that process that we were
talking to
about andrew of figuring out a
relationship to the symbol
what is hidden what is true and this
this is
kind of a schizoanalytical or or a very
creative pursuit as well of trying to
figure out
where ideas come from how do we relate
to them how do they react and the
symbols have to be
rediscovered and renewed in
in in a in a view that is is um
i don't know how to say that with with
the correct view rather than
as as some kind of parlor game or or you
know
there has to be some kind of study
behind you know you know uh you know
what is the ground of of all of these
symbols that bubble up from it you know
and um rather than them becoming some
kind of reified
formulaic kind of you know like very
very easily
you know we we have this potential to
create all these cults right
uh uh we have this very these days which
which is is a bit terrifying so yeah
i think there's a relationship between
that and and that practice that
that we're just talking about and then
the danger that is hidden within it
the madness of actually reinventing the
whole root of reality for yourself
it's a serious game it's it's it's a
game um
that's where master morality comes from
from confronting this abyss
and coming back to tell the story to
everyone else so there's a few that go
that are brave enough to risk uh
stepping out of this memetic house
within which we live
and there's those who follow those who
do that's that's for me that's the bard
absolute
that's master morality itself how do do
you have specific practices to
uh go down the abyss and rejuvenate the
ideas and memes and narratives
i would say not really i mean
what i try to do i'm trying
to give myself a real like strong
grounding in yoga and yoga meditation at
the moment almost as a preliminary to
anything else and that does uh points
involve i mean like where this overlaps
with say what andrew was talking about
with the
with that cabala exercise you know and
i'm sure like andrew perhaps
gets a sense of this as well from his
meditation practices like
meditating say on an object or a mantra
where there's the stages where it's like
you bring the object into awareness and
then there's like merging with the
object and then there's just like
feeling energetically the same as the
object you know as you were saying it's
um it's that source from which the
symbol arises
you yourself come directly into contact
with the symbol
is almost just like the way that this
energy is trying to communicate itself
but no i don't actually have any of
these like
techno shamanic practices uh unlocked
[ __ ] say chris gabriel super [ __ ]
interesting this like prodigy kid he's
20 years old he's got this youtube
channel called meme analysis they're
putting out
videos that are regularly getting
hundreds of thousands of views because
i mean he's really he's read so much
[ __ ] psychoanalysis
and he's taking a contemporary
psychoanalytic
lens to the depths of 4chan
and reddit and looking at these memes
the forever alone the duma the boomer
the gloom
and saying right what does this say
about the contemporary
psyche and what does it say that so many
people are being
drawn to these memes i think the great
case study which um which daniel can
probably write better than me is the
tech meme right that came up around the
time of donald trump
daniel would you be able to tell that it
was hyperstation per se hyperstation is
a superstition that
hyperstation no that's a word wow yeah
it's from the client it's the idea that
you
say something and by saying it and
infusing it with belief it has an effect
on reality and it becomes true it's kind
of a self-fulfilling prophecy that's
actively
put into display and so the keck thing
was
uh you know on 4chan it functions kind
of like an ouija board or a scrying
mirror
insofar as every post has an associated
number
so it's like every post that you make
has a number to it and then when all
those like you know seven digit number
and whenever those numbers are um
notable
when there's like repeated digits like
on twos and threes and fours
people like pay attention and so to
follow that more other than the other
ones because oh it's a double it's a
triple
fun okay this let's repeat this ad
infinitum so there was a meme that once
was about
okay pepe the frog and it said something
like trump will win and the post was
like seven seven seven seven seven seven
seven and so people started to really
just reinforce this belief tunnel which
was very
luck-based but also very meme based
obviously
but within that small field that was the
4chan and
window and the internet landscape which
is just
within this black mirror it gained so
much
so much momentum also in connection with
how people were making
sense of things that people started to
find coincidences
everywhere so apparently there was an
ancient egyptian god
that was a god of chaos that was also in
the shape of a frog
and the hieroglyph that represented that
frog looked like a dude on a computer
and people started to discover you know
old talo disco songs from the 60s
that had a frog with p-e-p-e under it
and the whole thing was about magic and
creating alternate holes and fabric of
space-time so
all of these coincidences they they kept
coming in
at a rate that was just reinforcing this
memetic
this this this aggregor
sounds like a schizophrenic state in in
some in some in some sense
right that's that's precisely what it is
it's uh schizoanalytical which is
another way at the losing way to say
it's magical
or ceremony and then what happened is
trump ended up retweeting the pictures
of this frog right and then i think even
did hillary clinton not also say
something about pepe's at which point
the chance went absolutely mad because
they were like oh my god it's true like
we've been rambling about all of this
and now they are actually talking about
it
and so it's like this bizarre thing
where this schizophrenic conspiracy
theory has been so
charged with collective libido that it's
actually it becomes real
i see you know exactly exactly
and that's i guess the the lessons that
so many
government contractors in the medic
warfare agencies they took lessons from
that
and now we see things like q anon pop up
and we see all of these
let's say artificial information
campaigns going uh going around
which are for me uh reiterations of this
of this lesson like oh belief is
malleable
oh we can use memes for this uh
then let's do it and let's do it as best
as we can using all this knowledge and
that's
what the alchemists knew and that's kind
of a dark way to be a sorcerer nowadays
that's uh
you know using alchemy for quick gains
here and there
yeah yeah well interesting
dark magic basically i mean
um to manipulation of belief for
purposes
um something that you know madison
avenue had us
you mentioned qanon yes
what does that have to do with that
because i think it also preys upon some
of the lessons that that
that existed on pepe namely uh
coincidence
namely um this technique of
predicting things saying this will
happen and then it happens and it
validates
namely you know speaking along magical
terms
or psychologically charged terms uh
being a meme in itself right being
something that's spread around memes
perhaps for a different targeted
audience not so much the young dudes of
4chan but
but trump's base overall but i think
it's just the same sort of
activity of you know i wouldn't i
wouldn't be surprised if you found
creative directors from from agencies
working in this stuff because it's
it's just the natural consequence the
natural
career transition if you're uh if you
know if you see that
blue church advertising is going down
the pipes and in a few years and i know
this is controversial but
there's something to it and i think that
coming back to performance you know is
it
is it something that you can create is
it that kind of performativism or is it
something that
you know uh isn't in a way a living
thing that that you can't really control
yeah it's a bit of both so look at look
at the best music or the best art it's
always a mad artist right something on
the verge of schizophrenia someone who
has an intimate knowledge of something
else
uh and and that you know the better the
matter the artist the better they are
not necessarily but there's a
relationship there right there's also
the other way around which
is laboratory music fabricated music
it's it's it's why
you know justin bieber has zero
longevity or
or pop music has zero longevity but
gotha
and faust lasts forever and the bible
lasts forever
so i think that we're talking about
different the same thing but on
different
ends of the same spectrum uh
so yes this could be created q and r
could be created perhaps in a laboratory
a memetic laboratory with creative
people
um but i think that there's a dimension
where you know you actually have to have
some real pathos
it's a it's a cheap kind of magic though
isn't it it's it's a it's a
it's uh like we were talking about a
sacrifice earlier it's like sacrificing
a lamb to get what you want or something
it's like
you know it's it's um it's probably very
appealing to some people to to
to go that route it's my mcdonald's how
do you you know how do you fight it how
do you how do you put
beams that destroy memes or or or
something like that like
like uh uh for me the alchemy
alchemical process might be like you you
would create you would you would create
a meme that would destroy this tendency
of
of of of driving people in saying or
unless you're an accelerationist i guess
i guess that
nick landis but he wants the world to
break open into this
schizophrenic state so that a new
synthesis will come or
i don't know um i mean i think what
you're driving
andrew is this need to inoculate
ourselves across
whatever this like schizophrenic
techno-social phenomenon is
and i think the fact that we exist
within this media landscape where we're
being bombarded by
images and sound bites and potentially
memes that we don't even
understand but that are so liberatingly
charged from the depths of wherever
anyway
there's a real like the alchemical
practice is to just notice that a that's
[ __ ] going
on and then and then discover the
practices or at least the spaces where
one can unplug from that and say like
okay
if that is the dynamic of where we're at
how can we channel it towards something
transcendent as opposed to getting
wrapped into the lowest common
denominator
well i said yeah and this is where i
remember
you guys can i
can yeah i i wanted to ask one thing
because
you know if you if you talk about these
uh
libid how do you say this this
discharged symbols
you know like in in prehistoric or
ancient times
it was legitimized through a priest or a
shaman or a true alchemist
right so but what you what you're
talking about this pepper that that is
like 20 year olds basically it's a bunch
of yeah but there there's no
to legitimization except that it's
chance
right yes because you said it so so
there's no
true alchemist fabricating those things
that because in that case you mentioned
it was just chance it was like a quick
coincidence and so
then it got it i would say the internet
itself
is the priest that is blessing it you
know it's the 4chan board that put the
right but on some
shared space it's like if we were in a
tribe and there was an agreed holy river
and all of a sudden ram's head showed up
severed in the holy river we'd be like
holy [ __ ] that's not good
that's precisely why some people talk
about the digital flood or the epistemic
armageddon
because tom whereas before we had
priests and then the blue church era of
the 20th century used to have some
academics actually being the validators
of what's true or not
you know they would look perhaps at the
me at the pepe phenomena
and say oh that's just coincidence and
throw some psychoanalysis through some
politics and sociology that is according
to the truth regime and
you know it's all settled and tightly
packed you can put it on cnn
but uh what where i think what it meant
what it shows is this this
is the fact that perhaps there's no one
actually driving today there's no
actually it shows that children are
driving
the whole thing you know babies right
babies are running the show
like i was watching uh like uh this you
know the social what's the social
dilemma thing on netflix right
and all those guys those it guys they're
they're brilliant asperger
kids who are are have really super high
iqs and no wisdom right
so no wonder they created a monster they
have no wisdom
and they have no authority there's no
authority there's no shaman
you know who is who is taking them
through the steps
towards to toward towards towards wisdom
so they're
they're they're they're just uh they're
just completely
um you know making it up as they go
along and so so
so again when then we have these figures
like greta
you know uh i think that it's basically
like a a child's crusade or something
i i i let me let me refine on that and
why i don't necessarily agree with you
so
i think it's a property of two things
one of them is the system so now the
system is decentralized whereas before
the institution was paramiddle and
there's someone at the top who has the
power to
say this is how it's going to be period
right and you know the academia and the
schools back in the day
there was like a clear chain of command
of truth this is this is where truth
will flow down the kabbalistic tree of
life for the societal pyramid
and that's it there's no other
opportunity
whereas today the properties of the
system of the internet of
technocapitalism
the internet as technology decentralized
its meaning making and then capitalism
creating an incentive
being the market for the proliferation
so the system has those properties in
itself which is even more dangerous than
having the children
run it um so that's one thing right
that's the system
argument it's it's of the system so it's
not the children it's the algorithms
that are running it is that sort of like
what you're saying or
it's the system being kind of the the
vessel
for unchained desire being rampant
this is the spectacle by gita board this
is uh the
autonomous collective intelligence of
techno capitalism according to nick land
which is collective human libido being
unchained
from any other vessel becoming
i think andrew you're right to say
children that is precisely the point
it's the childish libido that is
unconstrained that is not learned to
channel itself towards something higher
yeah it's this weird confluence between
the the youth culture
uh yeah hero you know worse you know
worship that alexander always talks
about
you know the rock star the movie star
the all these people being the ultimate
symbol of
of something but what it's sort of an
empty kind of
kind of uh kind of thing there's no
problem
it's self-terminating and it doesn't
lead to wisdom and transcendence and and
and you know real beauty and all those
things right
what do you think of jordan peterson
then because because he
he is he still rests on this
pyramidal uh structure of
of society he is like a professor and he
he charged the the symbols in a new way
you know so and he created
memes so so it's like uh it's like the
antitheath what you just said yeah
that's what i was sort of
that's what that's that's what we need
that kind of thing even if he was off in
in certain ways
but but but but i think i think that's
exactly the
the kind of the kind of thing that we
need yeah
is the jordan peterson type there is
there's a there is a problem with how
popular i don't know if we need it but
it's clearly
it's clearly a different way of what
daniel is describing
because it's not uh okay
okay so no no i mean it's a great great
point to bring up but
he was became big on the internet he
is a psychoanal psychologist that talks
about the bible and christianity so
already here this
cross-domain situation
he has no expertise he only has perhaps
expertise on psych
according to blue church in psychology
but having become big
on on the internet talking about
christianity becoming this leader for
this
for this male uh sort of more more male
movements is for me a symptom of
these dynamics that i described so it
was a very decentralized internet age
phenomena
that he had it all right and perhaps by
tapping into that variety of things that
they did
he damn it he put ahead
to a lot of desire that was already out
there
of people looking for meaning and
looking for for a way out an exit for
the current
uh yeah i think he kind of became the
archetype that was missing
in the culture and that also destroyed
him in a sense that it was it's too much
for one person to bear
it's like that has to be distributed
right
on some levels and he his view of sort
of the sovereign individual
kind of conquering and pulling himself
up by the bootstraps and
is is very is great but it's sort of
like the first part of the story
it needs to be completed by uh um
by a vision that you know where where
this responsibility is distributed i
think right
uh you know does that make any sense
what i'm saying like it has to be again
it does that that makes that kind of
change and it can't be
one sort of savior who who is you know
you know because then then the he
develops a kind of a christ complex and
then you know of course he gets
crucified
um absolutely like i think if he
had developed a community around him and
grown it
slowly it might have been a very
different story but in a sense
he tapped into this very primal
symbolic charge and then distributed it
entirely in a way that led people to
just be there this is the daddy i never
had
he's the savior as you said andrew he
just became this christ figure
you know you look at the youtube videos
and there's something like
quite eerily like it was like he's the
second coming of christ almost like
peterson's come
to save us i mean intriguingly as well
just based by what we've been saying
already
he also has a voice that sounds a bit
like a frog for a while
right round on the chance sure no i
think he took a photo with kermit the
frog
kind of unknowing about this whole
conspiracy
but that that exploded something off as
well um
there's something else i wanted to say
about him um
no it's gone from my mind yeah but i
agree with you
you're on point um
he got drawn into the political game
right he got drawn into the old battle
of left versus right
20th century west versus east you know
or
you know whatever like yeah there was a
there was a what's the word
manikin good or evil
sense of mission that he had which which
was powerful in a sense but you know i
don't know that the taoists say that
charisma as a kind of
sickness or something um i kind of felt
that about his charisma
and in some kind of way in retrospect
although although i think he was very he
was genuinely very heroic and brave in
what he did and he generally lifted a
lot of people up and and
so i so so i i don't want to sound like
i'm i'm
you know cutting him down
that's coming to mind yeah i so
owen you remember when we talked to mack
once and he said that
any critique of a contemporary sort of
left suw situation is recuperated as
white supremacy and recuperation is a
term that comes from
uh situation is theory which is the idea
that you know
che guevara you know the revolutionary
even revolutionary causes like the one
of shagovara eventually gets recuperated
into capitalism
even if it's by selling t-shirts that
says right
every sort of the 60s became uh
yoga moms in 2020 so
perhaps jordan peterson also got
recuperated by the by the machine by
being brought into this
field of you know capitalism versus
communism which is for me
um just just just a distraction from the
essential
um perhaps pathetic nature of what he
was actually tapping into i mean when he
when he was
making a million videos on youtube
youtube about the bible it being
uh it being um
hyperlinked and making videos about
christianity that had a million views i
think that's where
we're talking about the true energy
coming in but that obviously gets
recuperated
yeah yeah it's almost like it's almost
like when you become famous there are
two versions of you
you know you have you have the red
reductive version of you which becomes
kind of an avatar
for a certain ideology uh-huh and then
and then
your substance gets gets lost in the
noise and
and you know a certain amount of people
are aware of your substance but most
people just get your
your your um your your avatar
your you know your your uh
your ideological you know because he was
his critique
it was against ideology and then he
became a sort of ideologue himself
indoors there was or something about
that that
but isn't that also andrew greek tragedy
that
that the trades that live that lifts us
up are
exactly the same traits that bring us
down exactly
um yeah there's something very tragic
about it it's almost like unspeakable or
something
you know like in the sense like he died
or something like he just disappeared
and then
it's almost hard to speak about him now
because he's because what happened it's
like somebody somewhat
some person who's still out there is
like a ghost and and
you you talked about haunting so there's
this we're living in this time where
jordan peterson is sort of haunting us
in some kind of a way because he's he's
not he's not actually out there
doing his thing anymore but he's kind of
haunting the landscape
he's kind of like a ghost yeah exactly
no because we we all at some point will
fall out of time
you know when when the personality
traits and that what we learned just
doesn't fit the environment anymore
and then we become we then we become
ghosts and and
you know like not active actors anymore
that's a terror that's a terrifying
thought actually
perhaps that's why alexander talks about
the death of celebrity culture coming in
the next 10 years
and also why there's something to be
said perhaps of
the admission that we've already lost
that agency is
an enlightenment age relic alongside
with
the individual as a category of being
right the individual that does things in
the world i mean who are we napoleon or
not we're just
people in our time doing our things and
perhaps enter to what you said
talking about communities maybe it's
going to be about the network effects
logarithms maybe it's going to be about
the ideas being the protagonists not us
the ideas
oh i like that i like that a lot yeah
i like very much the idea that here as
we're speaking we're creating
an idea you know that that might that
might um
have some kind of momentum and you know
creative momentum i mean you i think you
already you
already can sense this you know it's
like um
it was actually quite funny um you know
i got a whatsapp message
it was yesterday and there was some guy
i i don't really know he got my he got
my number
and he texted me like for three minutes
that
um in regard of alexander bart and you
know that
the world is too masculine anyhow and
that i don't
should go down the path rebel wisdom but
it's like
you know that that we're still in this
battle of ideas and
and you know it's it's a culture war and
which ideas will
and which means so to speak will will
prevail in that
in the sequence of the dance we are
dancing eternally you know it's just
like
it's so weird you know it was not it is
not about alexander or rebel wisdom or
or
you know just like these these ever
recurring
ideas that that are haunting us
we are the you know the ideas have us
and not the other way around when i
started talking to john
i i john vervecky i started to
understand what he was saying about
dial logos um you know he has this idea
about dialogues being a genuine
spiritual practice
where you you kind of you know if you're
creating something like you know me and
me and tom get together and then we
start to create something
and then all the four of us kind of get
together and maybe
another element you know is is created
through through dialogue right so
there's this extra element that comes
through dialogos right dialoguing with
with truth
um and uh and that that's that seems to
be very very beautiful and that isn't an
individual
uh you know thing that's that's not a
lonely
romantic heroic journey it's more like
it's more like
um uh it's more like being the beatles
or something than being uh
i don't know being a you know a solo
artist
andrew let me ask you to like expand on
something because we're just talking
about peterson and obviously
around peterson emerged this
intellectual dark web movement and then
you wrote your piece the intellectual
deep web
which is this kind of i don't know
exactly what to describe it's some kind
of movement that we are part of in some
sense what is the intellectual
deep web as opposed to the intellectual
dark web
well um uh that was
i think alexander bienner was the guy
who had that idea and then i wrote i
wrote the article uh for rebel wisdom
because i was very i was very
dissatisfied with this movement actually
i was interested in peterson and his
biblical ideas and
i was following him but i i didn't i
wasn't a big believer in in the
intellectual deep web because
it seemed like a return to modernism and
you know which i thought was a positive
movement in some sense because
bringing back rationality and and that
kind of thing and then a sort of you
know it was a positive movement
but it didn't to me to me it it didn't
didn't
go deep enough it didn't go far enough
it didn't didn't have really
something to say which which turned me
on
on some level so so the idea that it
would a deep web
would be you know an exploration of you
know deeper issues of anthropology and
and and religion and um you know
and you know you know continental
philosophy not just positivism and
science and you know the the whole sort
of
um yeah i mean
just uh just just a deeper view that
wasn't i guess
not uh on a stage trying to be
a savior of some kind but but more like
based on
genuine relationships and friendships
and
yes there's a performative aspect you
know um
um but it kind of happens i think i
think
there's a there's an edge to it as well
because it's not slick it's not packaged
it's not
um uh it's not uh only you might there
might be
a political aspect to it but that's only
a very small part of it it might be an
ideological aspect but that's not not
the whole
uh whole story because like it's a
practice
like because is the dialogue it's a
space for dialogues to happen
right it's a living process it's
processed it's always
in process it never stops anywhere it's
end soft
it's my favorite new you know word end
soffit never ends it never ends and
you know means light that never ends and
even in
you know but you you make a
representation of a black sun because
because because in in space the light
has nothing to reflect on it right
so so so the the lunar aspect is the
mercury and that reflects wisdom and
but it's actually this endless source
right and
it never reifies it never stops it never
becomes
something um you know you know permanent
or
or final or um so so there's always an
open-endedness
a quality of open-endedness to to the
whole you know endeavor
i love this this is kabulis but it seems
like amazing all of the
intellectual dark web not jewish either
but
you know i just i love uh and soft thank
you
sorry dark phobias
i'll say so the dark web figures they
all in some sense or another i think
had quite a serious link to some kind of
political activism or some kind of
political controversy
and wound up being perhaps the last
breath of celebrity culture the
weinstein brothers peterson
ben shapiro joe rogan they're all these
like
monolithic internet superstars who have
humongous followings whereas what i
think is going off in this dialogic deep
web
praxis it's far more underground and
it's far
more about the networks and yes like one
or two people
within it like alexander are celebrities
but even alexander has kind of
backed away from his celebrity status a
bit as far as i can tell
and you know he's been pushed out of it
because it's not it's not a landscape
that's livable
in that in that environment of of
wokeness
you can't live there there's there's no
life there it's like
you have to go underground to maintain a
semblance
of truth in malcooth
you have to expend a tremendous amount
of energy and if the link to ensof is
severed
then it's just going to go down and that
linkage twice off through assad
you know reflecting is is the key and
you saw it imagination
is inspiration is is the life force
that comes it's something that is common
to so many good artists to the genuine
creators but it's also extremely
dangerous because you know
it if there's not already any temple in
yasad
that can protect you then you're gonna
like you know go out in the rain and
it's it's too much it's not for us
because we live in malcov
right